GPT-5.6 found a new
7,194-point Sidon construction.
A separate verifier checked
all 25,880,415 pair sums.
Vela routed the evidence to Defer.
Accepted scientific state changed by zero.
That separation is the product.
Models can propose work.
Frozen verifiers can check artifacts.
Vela can record evidence and apply policy.
But none of them can make the
protected scientific decision.
Verification is not acceptance.
For Build Week, Canopus gave GPT-5.6 one
exact mission: improve a mechanically
verified but unaccepted 7,193-point
subset of the 24-dimensional Boolean cube.
The registration binds the model, target
packet, artifact path, byte and time
budgets, a frozen verifier,
an expected Defer route, and
zero accepted-state change.
It explicitly forbids claims of
maximality, classification, acceptance, or
a world record.
Inside its bounded workspace, GPT-5.6 built
the exact conflict structure and found
a one-for-two exchange.
It removed baseline point 72, added
hexadecimal points 970f25 and 246891,
reconstructed 7,194 points, and
independently enumerated every pair sum
before handing off.
Then a separate, network-denied,
read-only verifier parsed the
frozen 359-kilobyte artifact.
It checked 7,194 distinct binary
points and generated all 25,880,415
unordered componentwise sums.
Zero collisions.
Exact claim binding.
Exit zero.
The worker never graded itself.
Canopus passed the
verified artifact to Vela.
Vela built a root-bound Receipt and signed
policy routed the proposal to Defer.
Clean-clone replay matched.
The public Observatory shows the whole
chain: mission, GPT-5.6 worker, artifact,
verifier, Receipt, and Defer.
The candidate lower bound advances from
7,193 to 7,194, while the accepted state
and the human decision remain untouched.
The boundary is real, not decorative.
In a separate formal mission, GPT-5.6
produced a Lean candidate with an unsolved
inverse goal and a dependency on sorry Ax.
The frozen verifier returned exit one.
Canopus produced no Receipt, no proposal,
no frontier commit, and no mutation.
Failed work stays failed.
Canopus 0.6.2 is public on npm with
SLSA provenance, composed against Vela
0.912.0, with the read-only
Observatory as its evidence surface.
Judges can inspect the package in ninety
seconds, or reproduce the exact public
frontier commit without
rebuilding Canopus.
This Codex task built Canopus, bounded
the GPT-5.6 mission, repaired two
fail-closed dogfooding defects,
shipped the release, and published the
governed evidence flow.
Give Codex a mission.
Verify the work.
Keep humans in authority.
Let agents do the work without
letting them declare truth.